10 chapter 11 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna Su chapter 11 Plain Speaking The longer I lived at Berwick
the more proud and happy I felt at having such a place. Our master and
mistress were respected and beloved by all who knew them; they were good and
kind to everybody and everything; not only men and women, but horses and
donkeys, dogs and cats, cattle and birds; there was no oppressed or ill-used
creature that had not a friend in them, and their servants took the same tone. If
any of the village children were known to treat any creature cruy they soon
heard about it from the Hall. The squire and Farmer gray had
worked together, as they said, for more than 20 years to get check Reigns on the
cart horses done away with, and in our parts you seldom saw them; and sometimes,
if mistress met a heavily laden horse with his head strained up she would stop
the car and get out, and reason with a driver in her sweet serious voice, and
try to show him how foolish and cruel it was. I don't think any man could
withstand our mistress. I wish all ladies were like her. Our master, too, used to
come down very heavy sometimes. I remember he was riding me towards home
one morning when we saw a powerful man driving towards us in a light pony Shas
with a beautiful little bay pony, with slender legs and a high-bred sensitive head and face.
Just as he came to the park gates the little thing turned toward them; the man,
without word or warning, wrenched the creature's head round with such a force
and suddenness that he nearly threw it on its hunches Recovering itself it was
going on, when he began to lash it furiously. The pony plunged forward, but
the strong, heavy hand held the pretty creature back with force almost enough
to break its jaw, while the whip still cut into him. It was a dreadful sight to
me, for I knew what fearful pain it gave that delicate little mouth; but master
gave me the word, and we were up with him in a
second. “Sawyer,” he cried in a stern voice, “is that pony made of flesh and blood?”
“Flesh and blood and temper,” he said; “he's too fond of his own will, and that won't suit
me.” He spoke as if he was in a strong passion. He was a builder who had often
been to the park on business. “And do you think,” said master sternly the treatment
like this will make him fond of your will?” “He had no business to make that
turn; his road was straight on!” said the man roughly. “You have often driven that pony
up to my place,” said master; “it only shows the creature's memory and intelligence;
how did he know that you were not going there again? But that has little to do
with it. I must say, Mr. Sawyer, that a more unmanly, brutal treatment of a little
pony it was never my painful lot to witness, and by giving way to such
passion you injure your own character as much N more, than you injure your horse;
and remember, we shall all have to be judged according to our works, whether
they be toward man or toward beast.” Master rode me home slowly, and I
could tell by his voice how the thing had grieved him. He was just as free to
speak to gentlemen of his own rank as to those below him; for another day, when we
were out, we met a Captain Langley, a friend of our masters he was trying
driving a splendid pair of grays in a kind of break. After a little conversation the
captain said: “What do you think of my new team, Mr. Douglas? You know, you were the
judge of horses in these parts, and I should like your
opinion.” The master backed me a little, so as to get a good view of
them. “They are an uncommonly handsome pair,” he said, “and if they are as good as
they look I sure you need not wish for anything better; but I see you still hold
that pet scheme of yours for worrying your horses and lessening their
power.” “What you mean,” said the other, “the check Reigns Oh, ah! I know that's a hobby
of yours; well, the fact is, I like to see my horses hold their head
up.” “So do I,” said master, “as well as any
man, but I don't like to see them held up;
that takes all the shine out of it. Now, you are a military man, Langley, and no
doubt like to see your regiment look well on parade, 'heads up', and all that; but
you would not take much credit for your drill if all your men had their heads
tied to a backboard! It might not be much harm on parade, except to worry and
fatigue them; but how would it be in a bayonet charge against the enemy, when
they want the free use of every muscle, and all their strength thrown forward? I
would not give much for their chance of victory. And it is just the same with
horses: you fret and worry their tempers, and decrease their power; you will not
let them throw their weight against their work, and so they have to do too
much with their joints and muscles, and of course it wears them up faster. You
may depend upon it, horses were intended to have their heads free, as free as
men's are; and if we could all act a little more according to common sense,
and a good deal less according to fashion, we should find many things work
easier; besides, you know as well as I that if a horse makes a false step, he
has much less chance of recovering himself if his head and neck are
fastened back. And now,” said the master, laughing I've given my hobby a good trot
out, can't you make up your mind to mount him, too, captain? Your example would go a long
way.” “I believe you are right in theory,” said the other, “and that's rather a hard
hit about the soldiers; but— —well— —I'll think about it,” and so they parted end of chapter